嘿，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的OpenGL系列教程
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my OpenGL series
那么今天我们要讲的是，如何在屏幕上渲染多个对象
so today we're going to be talking about, how we can render multiple objects on the screen
到目前为止，我们所做的只是在屏幕上渲染了一次ChernoLogo
so far all we've really done is we rendered that ChernoLogo on the screen once
并且我们还没有渲染过一个以上的对象
and we haven't like, we haven't rendered more than one object
所以我们会讲，渲染另一个物体或相同的物体需要什么
so we're going to talk about, what it takes to actually render another object or the same object
也许是在一个不同的位置或者一个全新的对象
maybe at a different position or an entirely new object
以及我们如何渲染多个东西
and how in general we can go about rendering multiple things
这将为以后设置一堆东西
this is going to set up a bunch of things for the future
就像我所有的视频一样，不用担心100年后的结果
as all of my videos seem to do, don't worry at the end in like 100 years from now probably
它会进入互联网，它会很好地连接起来，你们就会明白，一切都很顺利
it'll come into an internet, it'll tie it nicely, and you'll understand, everything works hopefully
所以这对以后的事情很重要
but yeah so this will be kind of important for things in the future
并且在我们开始讲之前先讲一下也是很好的
and also it's just a good thing to kind of talk about initially before we dive into it
那么如果我们看一下我们的代码，我会很快地运行它
so if we take a look at our code, I'm just gonna run it real quick
我们可以看看我们有什么，我们上次基本上添加了ImGui
so we can see what we have, we basically added ImGui last time
所以我们有了这个精致的Debug窗口
so that we had this kind of Debug overlay
顺便说一下，我解决了鼠标指针错位的问题
by the way, I solved that whole mouse pointer kind of being in the wrong place problem
那是因为我在电脑里使用的是Inter显卡
that was because I was using the Inter GPU inside my computer
我转到NVIDIA的显卡，它就可以了
I switched to the NVIDIA one, and it works fine
所以很明显这和Intel的显卡驱动有关
so clearly something to do with Intel's drivers
我以后可能会做个视频讲那个，但现在已经很完美了
I might make a video in the future talking about that, but it's perfect now as you can see
不管怎样，我们已经渲染了这个ChernoLogo
anyway, so we have this ChernoLogo being rendered
我们有这个模型矩阵，我们在这里用ImGui修改，一切看起来都很好
and we've got this model matrix that we're modifying here using ImGui, and everything seems fine
基本上我们今天的目标是在不同的位置渲染另一个
basically our goal for today's gonna be to render another one of these at a different position
我们来看看要怎么做
and we'll see what it takes for us to actually do that
那么如果我们看一下代码，没有什么太复杂的
so if we look at the code, nothing really too complicated is going on
但如果我们看一下真正绘制ChernoLogo的代码，就是这行代码
but if we take a look at the code that actually draws that ChernoLogo, it's this line over here
那么我们执行renderer.Draw，如果我把它按下alt f12键
so we do renderer.Draw, and if I just kind of alt f12 into that
你们可以看到两个，你们可以看到
so you can see both, you can see that
我们绑定了着色器，绑定了顶点数组，绑定了索引缓冲区
I'm we basically bind our shader, we bind our vertex array, we bind our index buffer
不是100%需要的，因为顶点数组已经绑定到索引缓冲区了
which actually isn't 100% necessary, because the vertex array already has a bind into the index buffer
但不管怎么说，然后我们会发出DrawCall，也就是这行代码
but anyway, and then we actually issue the DrawCall, which is this line over here
把ChernoLogo绘制到屏幕上的
which draws that ChernoLogo onto the screen
现在有一个东西决定了在哪儿绘制这个ChernoLogo
now here's a thing the thing that determines where this ChernoLogo gets drawn on
实际上，我们先来讨论这三行代码，以及它们的真正含义
in fact, let's just discuss these three lines first of all, and what they actually mean
所以shader.Bind很重要
so shader.Bind is important
因为它为我们的GPU绑定了一个用于渲染的程序
because it binds a program for our GPU to actually use to render
不管我们渲染什么，那就是着色器
whatever we're trying to render, that's the shader
至于着色器，很多人认为着色器很重要
the shader, a lot of people again think of shaders is really important
这样你们就能真正理解着色器是什么
that you are actually understand what shaders are
着色器也被OpenGL称为程序，字面上有一些着色程序
shaders which are also called programs by OpenGL, are literally that there are shader program
有一些东西可以让我们说，一些东西将如何被渲染
there's something that allows us to say, how something will be rendered
我们基本上是在告诉GPU该做什么，那非常重要
we're basically telling the GPU what to actually do, that's really important
它会被录下来，这与光线或阴影之类的东西无关
it goes tape, it's nothing to do with like lighting or shading or anything like that
这只是我们给GPU的指令，比如如何，在哪里，为什么等等
it's literally just us giving instructions to the GPU, as to how and where and why and whatever
我们想绘制我们要绘制的东西
we want to actually draw what we're trying to draw
那在第一步中非常重要，然后我们绑定顶点数组
that's really important that step one, then we bind the vertex array
也就是，再说一次，包含所有实际数据的数组
which is, again, the array that contains all of the actual data
所以程序或着色器会说，该如何处理这些数据
so the program or the shader says, what to do with the data
这个顶点数组就是我们要用到的数据
and this vertex array is the data that we're going to do stuff with
所以这包括我们的顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区，那就是我们现在所有的
so this includes our vertex buffer and our index buffer, that's all that we've got at the moment
顶点缓冲区当然包含了所有的顶点数据
and vertex buffer of course contains all of the vertex data
包括我们试图渲染纹理坐标的每个点的位置
including including the positions of each kind of point that we're trying to render texture coordinates
我想那就是我们现有的，但是如果我们绘制一些更复杂的东西
I think that's what we've got, but if we were drawing something a bit more complex
我们可能还有其他的东西比如顶点颜色法向量，法向量，切线
we might have other other things in there like vertex colors or normal or by normal or tangents or
在顶点数据中有很多东西，我们以后会讲到
there's a lot of things that you can put into vertex data, which we will get into in the future
索引缓冲区当然包含顶点缓冲区的索引，这样就知道渲染是什么了
the index buffer of course contains the indices into the vertex buffer, so that we actually know like what render
索引缓冲区包含顶点缓冲区的索引
the index buffer contains the indices into the vertex buffer
因此我们可以选择我们真正想要渲染的顶点
so that we can choose what which vertices we actually want to render
如何把它们组合在一起，最后绘制出元素
and how to kind of assemble all them together, and then finally draw elements just says
嘿，你们知道的，用索引缓冲区访问顶点缓冲区
hey, you know, using that index buffer access the vertex buffer
然后分别在所有这些顶点上调用着色程序
and call the shader program on all of those vertices individually
让它绘制并最终将我们的对象恢复到屏幕上
to actually get it to draw and eventually restoring our object onto the screen
所以那就是一种对之后渲染另一个ChernoLogo需要什么的总结
so that's kind of a bit of a summary of what it takes to render that one kind of Cherno later
所以如果我们想渲染另一个，它看起来会完全一样
so if we want to render another one in like with the, it'll look exactly the same
但我们希望它在屏幕上的其他地方
but we want it to be somewhere else on the screen
我们要怎么做，我们需要改变什么
how do we do that, and what do we actually need to change
好了，让我们考虑一下，首先，着色器需要改变一下
well okay, let's think about it, first of all, the shader does that need to change well
这个着色器是，如果我们看一下我们的着色器是什么样的
the shader is kind of, if we take a look at what our shader even looks like
就是这个东西
it's just this thing over here
顶点着色器只是从顶点缓冲区中接收一些数据，也就是这里的这部分
the vertex shader just takes in a bunch of data from the vertex buffer, which is this part over here
也可以直接从mat4作为统一变量
and also just directly from mat4 as uniforms
然后就是设置gl_Position，也就是顶点的位置
and then well set gl_Position, which in terms of where the vertices are going to be
然后将这个纹理坐标输出到着色器管道的下一个阶段
and then also outputs this texture coordinate to the next stage of the shader pipeline
对于我们来说，就是片段着色器
which for us is the fragment shader
基本上也就是接收，v_TextCoord就是来自顶点缓存区
which basically takes in, that TextCoord from the vertex buffer
不好意思，来自顶点着色器
sorry, from the vertex shader
然后还从CPU拿到了两个统一变量
and then also takes in two uniforms from the CPU
然后使用纹理坐标，对纹理进行采样
and then just basically samples the texture, using the texture coordinate
然后输出它从纹理采样中得到的颜色到这个output color
and outputs the color that it retrieves from that texture sampling into this output color over here
在我们最后这个片段缓冲区中
in our final frame buffer
所以那就是着色器的作用
so that is how that's what our shader does
如果我们认为着色器是特定于任何位置的，不
so if we think about the shader is a specific to any kind of position, well no
因为它以某种方式获取到了了位置，不是吗
because it takes the position in from some way, doesn't it
我们看看它从哪里得到这个位置
well, let's look at where it gets the position from
所以你们可能注意到的第一个东西就是那个，是的
so the first thing you might notice is that, yes
上面这里有一个position属性，意思是这个来自顶点缓冲区
we have a position attribute up here, which means that this is coming in from the vertex buffer
那么我们可以做的，做为实现这个的其中一种方法是
so what we could do, as just one of the ways that we could do this is
我们可以提供不同的顶点位置
we could supply different vertex positions
现在那需要一个额外的顶点缓冲区
now what that would require is having an additional vertex buffer
因为我们需要创建第二个顶点缓冲区
because we would need to create a second vertex buffer
它包含了ChernoLogo的第二个实例的所有位置
which contains all of the positions of the second instance of the ChernoLogo
然后我们可以用那个把它们放在某个地方
and then we could use that to actually put them somewhere
并且这是可行的，很好，这是实现这个的一种方法
and that will work, that's fine, that's one way to do things
我们看一下，如果有其他的方法
let's see, if there's another way
那么实际上发生在这儿的另一件事
so the other thing that actually happens here
你们可以看到这个位置也乘上了这个统一变量
you can see that this position also gets multiplied with this uniform
也就是我们的模型视图投影矩阵
which is our model view projection matrix
那么除了改变属性和那个顶点缓冲区，我们还可以做的是
so what we could also do instead of changing that attribute and that vertex buffer is
我们可以就改变那个模型视图投影矩阵统一变量，对吧
we could just change that model view projection matrix uniform, right
我们基本上可以给它一个矩阵，它应用了不同的变换
we could basically just provide it with a matrix, that had a different transformation applied
本质上就像一个不同的模型矩阵
like a different model matrix essentially
它将我们的对象放置在场景中的其他地方
which positioned our objects somewhere else in the scene
然后当它与现有的顶点属性相乘时
and then when that got multiplied with that existing kind of vertex attributes that we have
那些现有的位置，它就会把它们放在屏幕的其他地方
those existing positions, it would put them somewhere else in the screen
所以那就是两种方法，或者说另外两种我们可以修改的数据
so that's kind of the two ways right now, or other two pieces of data that we could actually modify
以便让两个ChernLogo出现在屏幕上的不同位置
in order to get two ChernLogo to show up in different places on the screen
所以在这种情况下，我要做的是，不去管顶点缓冲区
so in this case, what I would do is, I would leave the vertex buffer alone
事实上，现在我认为，它被设定为(100, 200)，或者它没有被标准化
and in fact, right now I think, it's set to like (100, 200), or like it's not kind of normalized
我可能会把它调成0左右
I'd probably just set it up to be scented around zero
然后我会提供两个不同的模型视图矩阵，模型视图投影矩阵
and then I would just provide two different model view matrix, model view projection matrices
把它们放在屏幕的其他地方
to actually position them somewhere else in the screen
因为有两个顶点缓冲区是我们GPU中不必要的内存使用
because having two vertex buffers is an unnecessary kind of memory usage that we have in our GPU
我们还需要重新绑定它们，这并不像提供一个不同的统一变量那么快
and also we need to rebind them, which is not as fast as just providing a different uniform
事实上，每次绘制时提供一整个不同的统一变量是很常见的
in fact, it's pretty common to just provide a whole set of different uniforms every time you draw
然而对于顶点缓冲区
whereas a vertex buffer
在这种情况下，我们不需要改变它
we don't necessarily need to change it in this case
所以我们不需要担心那个
so we don't need to actually worry about that
顺便说一下，我刚才说过
by the way, I did just say
重新绑定一个不同的顶点缓冲区要比设置统一变量慢
that rebinding a different vertex buffer is slower than uniforms
其实不是这样的，把统一变量交给GPU实际上涉及到
that's not actually true, sending uniforms over to the gpu actually involves
将数据从CPU传输到GPU
transferring data from the CPU to the GPU
所以我并不是说，这样做会更快
so I didn't actually mean, it's physically faster to do that
我只是在讨论事实
I'm just talking about the fact
我们不需要有两个冗余的数据集来绑定它们
that we don't need to have two redundant sets of data that we need to bind between
并且它让我们感觉我们有两个不同的对象
and basically it makes it feel like we have two different objects
在这种情况下，我们只需提供一个不同的模型视图矩阵就容易得多
in this case, it's a lot easier for us just to provide a different model view metrics
并那就是模型视图投影矩阵
and that's it a model view projection metrics
就是这样，让我们来看看，我们怎么做
and that's it, so let's take a look at, how we might do that
那么如果我返回Application.cpp
so if I go back to our Application.cpp
实际上我首先要做的是，关闭这个renderer
what I'm actually gonna do first of all, close this renderer thing
我只需要考虑我在这里提供的这些位置
emmm is, I'm just going to like think about these positions that I've actually supplied here
那么这些都是纹理坐标它们被填满了，不管任何需求，不用担心它们
so these are all texture coordinates they're filled with whatever need, don't worry about them
但这里我们有一个100×100的像素或单位
but what we have here is we have a 100 by 100 pixel or unit
在这个例子中，一个单位就是一个像素，这儿这个正方形
in this case, one unit is one pixel, a square here
所以我要做的就是让它以(0, 0)为中心
so what I'm going to do is, I'm going to make it so that it's centered around (0, 0)
因为现在它从100到200，那不是很大
because right now it kind of goes from 100 to 200, and that's not great
因为这意味着如果我们提供任何形式的变换
because it means that if we provide any kind of translation to it
它将从这个作为原点
it's going to be from this as the origin
所以我们没有原点，它实际上是0，我希望原点是0
so we don't have an origin, that's actually zero, and I would like our origin to be zero
所以我要做的是，因为它需要是100×100
so what I'm going to do is, because it needs to be 100 by 100
因为我要让左界和下界都是-50，然后右边的边界是50
as I'm going to make the kind of left bound and the bottom bound -50, and then the right bound 50
因为这是一个100x100的正方形，所以我要改变这个
because that gives us a 100 by 100 square, so I'll change this
基本上任何100的值都要改成-50
basically anything that is 100 needs to be changed to be -50
所有的200都要改成50，好了
and everything that is 200 needs to be changed to be 50, okay
所以这里是-50，这里也是-50
so this is going to become -50, and this is also going to be -50
我把所有的100换成-50，就像那样
I'll change all the 100 right now to be -50, just like that
然后这些就变成了50
and then these are going to become 50
我在这里腾出一个空间，这样所有的东西都能完美地对齐
and I'll just relieve a space here, so that everything kind of lines up perfectly
好了，完成，如果我们按f5来看这个
okay, there we go, done, so if we just hit f5 to look at this
我们应该看到的是因为(0, 0)是屏幕的左下角
what we should see is because (0, 0) is the bottom left of our screen
如果我设置它的位置为(0, 0)
if I set the position of this to (0, 0)
它应该以零点为中心
what it should be is kind of centered around our zero point
现在它有点难以看到，另外，我认为我们有一个相机变换应用
now it's a bit hard to see, and additionally I think we have a camera transformation applied
如果我快速点击这里的停止键
so if I just hit stop here real quick
我看了看它提供的模型视图投影矩阵
and I take a look at the model view projection matrix that it were actually supplying
这是我们的视图矩阵，可以看到它被平移了-100，我不用担心这个
so this is our view matrix, you can see that it's translated -100, I'm not going to worry about that
现在我要对相机做的就是让它的平移为0
what I'm going to do for now for the camera is just leave it to be a translation of zero
所以我把这些代码都留在这里，有点多余，因为显然我们没有任何平移
so I'll kind of leave all this code here, it is a bit redundant, because obviously we have no translation
所以这个矩阵只是一个单位矩阵，这意味着我们可以不乘它
so this matrix is just an identity matrix, which means that we might as well not multiply it at all
但我们以后会改变这些东西，那就是为什么我要留下代码
but we'll change this stuff in the future, that's why I'm leaving the code
所以我们有这个，只是外面变得更黑了
so we have this over here, and it just got a lot darker outside
现在下雨了，如果这个视频里的灯光变了，我很抱歉
and now it's raining, so if the lighting in this video changes, I'm sorry
但墨尔本的天气就是这样的，这个视图矩阵基本上就是
but that's how Melbourne weather works, okay, so this view matrix is basically just
我们的相机没有任何平移
we don't have any transmission applied to our camera
它在中间，在默认位置，也就是0 0 0
it's just in the kind of middle, it's in the default position, which is just 0 0 0
所以如果我们现在看这个，现在我们没有那个变换
so if we look at this now, now that we don't have that transformation
如果我把这个设置为(0, 0)，你们可以看到这个ChernoLogo是居中的
if I just set this to (0, 0), you can see that basically this ChernoLogo is kind of centered
中心点是(0, 0)
the center point is that zero is zero
当然外面的x和y都是- 50
of course it goes negative to 50 outside in both x and y
所以那就是我们现在要讲的内容，这样我们就能达成共识了
so that's where we're out right now, just so that we're on the same page
所以现在我要做的是渲染这个东西两次
so now what I'm going to do is I'm going to render this thing twice
我要改变这儿模型视图投影的统一变量
except what I'm going to do is change that model view projection uniform here
所以至于颜色，我们可以保留相同的颜色，这一点无关紧要
so the color, we can leave the same color, does not matter at this point
不论如何我们在渲染一个纹理，不会用这个颜色或其他什么来吸引它
because we're rendering a texture anyway, and we're not tempting it by this color or whatever
所以这还不如不存在
so this is just might as well not exist
事实上，我可能会停止设置它，因为它在代码方面令人困惑
in fact I'm probably gonna stop setting it, because it's just confusing in terms of code
所以我现在需要绑定着色器，你们会注意到
so I need to bind the shader now, you'll note that
当然，渲染一个绘制确实需要绑定着色器
of course render a drawer does actually bind the shader
那挺好的，但我们需要去设置统一变量
that's all fine, but we need to set up uniforms
并且为了设置统一变量，我们需要激活一个已绑定的着色器
and in order to set uniforms, we need to have an active shader bound
这样我们就把它们绑定到右边的这个统一变量上
so that we can bind them to the right uniforms
或者这样我们就可以将统一变量绑定到正确的着色器上
or so that we can bind the uniforms to the right shader
所以基本上就可以绘制了
so we need to basically and draw
那么首先，我们知道绑定的着色器已经在这里被激活了
so first of all, we know that shader bind already is activated here
所以我们不需要再绑定了，基本上我要做的就是绑定我的着色器
so we don't need to bind again, so what I'm basically going to do is I'm going to bind my shader
然后在我绘制之前，我要像这样设置这个统一变量两次
and then before I draw, I'm just going to set this uniform twice like this
对吧，所以在每次绘制之前，我都要设定一个模型视图投影统一变量
right, so before every draw, I'm setting out a model view projection uniform
在我设置第二个之前，我实际上需要做的当然就是改变它
now what I need to do before I set the second one is of course actually change it
所以我要做的就是
so what I'm going to do is
我们有这个模型矩阵，这是我们的第一个translation
we have this model matrix here, which is kind of our well our first translation
我要对translation做的就是到上面这里，复制并粘贴它
what I'm going to do is go up here to translation, copy and paste that
我把这个叫做translationA和translationB
I'm going to call this translation a and translation b
我把这个x设为400而不是200，然后如果我往下看
I'm going to put this one maybe at 400 x instead of 200 x, and then if I go down here
我要用translationA来得到这儿的第一个模型矩阵
I'm going to use translation a to get the first model matrix here
并且那就是我们要发送的，事实上，为了让这个保持更清晰一些
and that's what we're going to actually send, and in fact, just to just to keep this a bit cleaner
我将把这个和SetUniformMap4像那样一起包含在这个作用域中，好了
I'm actually going to enclose this in a scope along with that SetUniformMap4 just like that, okay
所以那就是我们设定的第一个统一变量
and so that's basically our setting the first uniform
也许我会把drawer放进这个作用域中
and maybe I'll even put the drawer into the scope
这样就讲得通了，这是一种绘图操作
so that it kind of makes sense, this is kind of one operation to draw
并且现在我要对这里做同样的事情
and now I'm going to do the exact same thing to what we have over here
只是我们要用translationB来代替，所以是一样的
it's just that we're going to use translation b instead, so identical same thing
只是我们用的是translationB
it's just that we're using translation b instead
好了，只有在第一次运行这个循环时，我们才需要这个绑定的着色器
okay, and we need this shader of bind really only for the first time we run through this loop
因为drawer会绑定那个着色器，永远不会解绑它
because drawer will bind that shader, and never unbind it anyway
并且因为我们没有绑定其他着色器
and since we're not binding additional shaders
这一切就都可以了，你们想让这个代码更稳健一点
this will all work, you want to make this code a bit more robust
更明智的做法是把它搬到这里来
it would be wiser to actually move that into here
再说一次，如果你们在已绑定的着色器上调用BindShader
again, if you call BindShader on the shader that's already bound
这有点多余，有点慢，有点浪费性能
that's a bit redundant, that's a bit slow, that's a bit of a waste of performance
通常是在更复杂的设置中，如真实游戏引擎或图像引擎
usually in more complicated setups, such as a natural game engine or a graphics engine
你们会有一个缓存系统，那就像挂起一分钟
you would have a some kind of cache system, that would be like hang on a minute
你们试图绑定已绑定的着色器
you're trying to bind the shader that's already bound
那是多余的，我不会运行那个OpenGL调用
that's redundant, I'm just not gonna run that OpenGL call
显然，我们没有像那样的任何设置，但对于这个例子来说，还是不错的
we don't have anything like that set up obviously, but it'll be fine for this example
好了，所以translation A和B的设置不同
okay, so translation a and b set up differently
并且现在我要做的就是修复这些ImGui错误
and now what I'm going to do here is as I fix these ImGui errors
我要确保我们有一个translationA
I'm actually going to make sure that we have translation a
并且我还会添加translationB到这个ImGui窗口
and I'm also going to add translation b into this ImGui window as well
所以我们有像那样的a和b，现在按f5，看看我们得到了什么
so we'll have a and b just like that, now let's hit f5, and see what we get alright
看看这个，我们有两个ChernoLogos，让我把这个移开
check this out, so we have two ChernoLogos, let me just move this out of the way
并且如果我修改第一个，你们可以看到，它动了
and if I modify that first one, you can see, it moves
第一个移到这里，我可以上下左右移动
the first one over here, and I can move it up and down or left right
然后这里的第二个也是通过我们这里的2D滑块修改的
and then also the second one over here is modified via that 2D slider that we have over here
很酷的东西，所以基本上就那样，那就是你们渲染两个对象的方式
pretty cool stuff, so that's basically it, that's how you render two objects
实际上，我们在这里所做的是，渲染了相同的对象两次
really all we're doing here is, we're rendering the exact same object twice
我们没有改变任何东西，除了一个统一变量，我们这样做的原因是
we're not changing anything except for a single uniform, and the reason we're doing that is
因为我们想在实际屏幕上显示两个不同的位置
because we wanted to show up in two different positions on our actual screen
现在你们可能会想，好了，好吧，酷，那就是我渲染多个对象的方式
now you might be thinking okay, well, cool, that's how I ran to multiple objects
所以如果我想要放弃一些贴图地图，也许我可以创造一款2D游戏
so if I want to surrender some kind of tile map, maybe I'm making like a game, 2D game
我有像这样的层次，这只是一个贴图地图
and I have like this kind of level, that's just a tile map
我想我只要写一个for循环就可以直接实现这个了
I guess I just write a for loop that goes ahead and does this
不，这并不是渲染所有内容的解决方案
no, this isn't the solution to rendering everything
因为如果你们那样做的话
because if you do that
如果你们有一个渲染1000个贴图在屏幕上的满循环
if you just have a full loop that renders 1000 tiles on the screen
那将会非常慢，因为这是1000个绘制调用，并且就是那样的
that's gonna be pretty slow, because that's 1000 draw calls, and you it's just that
它一点都不会快，你们可能会注意到非常低的帧率
there's no, it's not gonna be fast at all, you'll probably notice very poor frame rates
我的意思是，在不错的硬件上，它仍然可能是60
I mean it still probably will be about 60 on decent hardware
因为在这里没有太多的渲染在机器上的1000次绘制调用，难道不可怕吗
because there's nothing much to render here in 1000 draw calls on a pc, isn't awful
但你们实际可以做些叫做批处理的在一个单独的绘制调用中绘制它
but you can actually draw that in a single draw call by doing something called batching
也就是把所有的贴图都塞进一个顶点缓冲区
which is where you actually shove all of your tiles into one vertex buffer
然后不像我在这里做的那样
and then have kind of instead of doing it the way that I did it here
就是我只修改统一变量
which is I'm just changing the uniform
你们实际上可以用我提到的另一种方法，基本上也就是
you can actually do the other method that I mentioned, which is basically instead of having
我们基本上是在改变顶点缓存中的顶点位置
we're basically changing the vertex positions that are in the vertex buffer
并且如果你们把那个设置好了的话
and if you set that up
但不是有两个不同的顶点缓冲区
but instead of having two different vertex buffers
而是你们把它们都塞进一个顶点缓冲区
you shove it all into one vertex buffer
然后你们就可以一次渲染所有的东西，所有的点都已经在那里了
and then you kind of just render everything all in one go, and all the dot is already there
因为顶点缓冲区非常大，它包含了你们拥有的每个贴图的所有位置
because the vertex buffer is very large, and it contains all the positions for every single tile you have
那比你们直接去绑定一个着色器要快1000倍
that would be 1000 times faster than if you go ahead and you bind a shader
修改统一变量，在1000个贴图中添加更多元素
you change the uniform and you do greater elements for 1000 tiles
好了，并且我们肯定会探索使用这种批处理渲染方法
okay, and we are absolutely going to explore doing that kind of batching rendering method
因为这是就像2D游戏，有大量2D的渲染，这是必须的
because it's like for 2D games, it's a lots of 2D rendering, it's a must
即使你们渲染的是布局
even if you're rendering like layouts
或者像你们知道的文本之类的东西，对于文本来说，这是至关重要的
or like kind of you know text stuff like that, for text, it's vital
因为你们在文本中渲染的每一种字符都是一个单独的绘制调用
because every kind of character that you render in text is a separate draw call
或者它是一个单独的，比如方形
or it's a separate like quad
并且我们不希望它们是独立的绘制调用，所以这就是
and we don't want them to be separate draw calls, so this is
我们很快就会讲到它
we'll definitely cover it in the future very soon probably
但我这样做的原因是，这可能是一种合理的方式
but the reason I did it this way is because this is kind of probably the way that makes sense
并且这可能是最简单的方法，也非常非常有用
and it's probably the most simple way, and it's also really really useful
如果在一个相当复杂的3D对象下，这就是100%，我们实际上会怎么做
if we were under a 3D objects that were quite complex, this is 100%, how we would actually do that
此外，它还引入了我们需要讨论的最重要的东西之一
and additionally it opens up one of the most important things that we need to talk about
这两个对象的不同之处仅仅是统一变量
which is the thing that is different about these two objects is just the uniforms
所以我们最终需要研究的是一种叫做材质的东西
so what we need to eventually get into is something called a material
材质其实就是一个着色器和一堆统一变量
and a material is really just a shader and a bunch of uniforms
并且我们以后会讲到那个的
and we'll get into that in the future
所以如果你们想让我继续说这两个东西的话，可以在下方留言
so leave a comment below as to if you want me to continue with this kind of two stuff
以及在下一期中介绍批处理渲染器，因为我可能会这样做
and cover the batch renderer in the next episode, because I'll probably end up doing that
我想，但除此之外，我们可以谈谈材质
I think, but otherwise, we might talk about materials and
开始做一些更令人兴奋的事情，这两个主题都很重要
start getting into some more exciting things like that, both topics are very important
无论如何，我们都要讲到它们的，它们真的很常见
and we'll have to cover them, anyway, and they're very seeing
那么可以在下方留言，并为任何提到你们赞同的评论点赞
so just leave a comment below, and thumbs up any comments that mentioned which one you agree with
我们将在下一期看到我们会做什么
and we'll see what we can do for the next episode
无论如何，我希望你们喜欢这个视频，如果喜欢，那就为它点个赞吧
anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video, if you did, hit the like button
也可以通过访问patreon.com/TheCherno来帮助支持这个系列教程
you can also help support the series by going to patreon.com/TheCherno
像往常一样，非常感谢我的支持者们
huge thank you as always to all my lovely supporters
每期视频的所有源码都是为支持者提供的
all the source code for every single video is up for patrons
所以一定要支持这个系列教程
so definitely support this series
如果你们对获取源代码感兴趣的话
if you're interested in getting the source code
并且还有很多为了感谢你们的支持的其他奖励
and there's also a bunch of other awards to thank you for your support
下次见，拜拜
I will see you guys next time, goodbye